בסרטון קודם, דיברתי על
systems of equations, and I sort of brushed
ליניארי 00:00:15,800 --&gt;
aside the discussion of actually computing
solutions to these systems.
00:00:19,690 3 הוא
And while it’s true that number-crunching
is something we typically leave to the computers,
מבחן לקמוס טוב
digging into some of these computational methods
אם אתה באמת
מבין מה קורה
this is really where the rubber meets the
או לא, שכן 00:00:31,680
road.
--&gt; 00:00:32,680 00:00:32,680
Here I want to describe the geometry behind
a certain method for computing solutions to
--&gt; 00:00:36,379 8
these systems, known as Cramer’s rule.
9 הקפד לצפות
The relevant background needed here is an
understanding of determinants, dot products,
בסרטונים הרלוונטיים בנושאים
and of linear systems of equations, so be
אלה אם אינך
מכיר או חלוד.
אבל קודם!
אני צריך לומר
is not the best way for computing solutions
מראש שהכלל של
to linear systems of equations.
קריימר 00:00:56,379 --&gt;
Gaussian elimination, for example, will always
be faster.
00:00:58,010 00:00:58,010
So why learn it?
--&gt; 00:01:01,950 16
Think of this as a sort of cultural excursion;
it’s a helpful exercise in deepening your
17 עוזר לגבש
knowledge of the theory of these systems.
רעיונות מאלגברה לינארית,
Wrapping your mind around this concept will
כמו המערכות
הקובעות והלינאריות, על
seeing how they relate to each other.
ידי 00:01:19,960 --&gt;
Also, from a purely artistic standpoint, the
ultimate result is just really pretty to think
00:01:24,619 22 23
about, much more so that Gaussian elimination.
יעבדו מערכות
Alright, so the setup here will be some linear
system of equations, say with two unknowns,
עם מספר גדול
x and y, and two equations.
יותר של לא
In principle, everything we’re talking about
ידועים, ומספר זהה
של משוואות.
אבל לשם הפשטות,
to hold in our heads.
דוגמה קטנה יותר
So as I talked about in a previous video,
you can think of this setup geometrically
היא נחמדה יותר
as a certain known matrix transforming an
unknown vector, [x; y], where you know what
00:01:46,349 --&gt; 00:01:50,599
the output is going to be, in this case [-4;
29 -2].
זכור, העמודות של
you how the matrix acts as a transform, each
המטריצה הזו מספרות
one telling you where the basis vectors of
the input space land.
00:02:06,250 --&gt; 00:02:10,899
So this is a sort of puzzle, what input [x;
y], is going to give you this
33 סוג התשובה
output [-4; -2]?
שתקבל כאן יכולה
Remember, the
להיות תלויה בשאלה
אם הטרנספורמציה נמעכת
all of space into a lower dimension.
או לא 00:02:44,299
That is if it has zero determinant.
--&gt; 00:02:46,080 00:02:46,080
In that case, either none of the inputs land
on our given output or there are a whole bunch
--&gt; 00:02:51,849 39
of inputs landing on that output.
40 המרחב ה-n-ממדי
But for this video we’ll limit our view
to the case of a non-zero determinant, meaning
המלא בו הוא
the output of this transformation still spans
התחיל; כל קלט
נוחת על פלט
and every output has one and only one input.
אחד ויחיד 00:03:12,549
One way to think about our puzzle is that
we know the given output vector is some linear
--&gt; 00:03:14,840 44
combination of the columns of the matrix;
x*(the vector where i-hat lands) + y*(the
חשב מה הם
vector where j-hat lands), but we wish to
בדיוק x ו-y.
כמעבר ראשון, הרשו
is wrong, but in the right direction.
לי להראות רעיון
The x-coordinate of this mystery input vector
is what you get by taking its dot product
ש-00:03:18,829 --&gt;
with the first basis vector, [1; 0].
00:03:23,340 48 49
Likewise, the y-coordinate is what you get
by dotting it with the second basis vector,
תוצרי הנקודה
[0; 1].
עם הגרסה שעברה
So maybe you hope that after the transformation,
טרנספורמציה של
וקטור המסתורין עם
versions of the basis vectors will also be
הטרנספורמציה 00:03:41,939 --&gt;
these coordinates x and y.
00: 03:43,590
That’d be fantastic because we know the
transformed versions of each of these vectors.
00:03:43,590 --&gt; 00:03:50,400
There’s just one problem with this: it’s
not at all true!
55 לפני
For most linear transformations, the dot product
ואחרי השינוי יהיו
שונים מאוד.
לדוגמה, יכול להיות
pointing in the same direction, with a positive
שני וקטורים בדרך
dot product, which get pulled away from each
other during the transformation, in such a
כלל 00:04:04,959 --&gt;
way that they then have a negative dot product.
00:04:09,270 60 61
Likewise, if things start off perpendicular,
with dot product zero, like the two basis
יישארו מאונכים לאחר
vectors, there’s no guarantee that they
הטרנספורמציה, וישמרו על
מכפלת הנקודה האפסית.
בדוגמה שבה הסתכלנו,
certainly aren’t preserved.
dot products
They tend to get bigger since most vectors
are getting stretched.
00:04:27,140 --&gt;
In fact, transformations which do preserve
dot products are special enough to have their
00:04:30,950 66 וקטורים
own name: Orthonormal transformations.
מאונכים זה
These are the ones which leave all the basis
לזה עם
יחידת אורך.
לעתים קרובות אתה חושב על אלה כמטריצות סיבוב.
תואם לתנועה קשיחה,
squishing or morphing.
ללא מתיחה, 00:04:53,000
Solving a linear system with an orthonormal
matrix is very easy: Since dot products are
--&gt; 00:04:58,920 73
preserved, taking the dot product between
the output vector and all the columns of your
מוצרים בין וקטור
matrix will be the same as taking the dot
הקלט לכל וקטורי
הבסיס, שזהה למציאת
the coordinates of the input vector.
00:05:13,599 --&gt; 00
So, in that very special case, x would be
the dot product of the first column with the
:05:18,690 77 רוב
output vector, and y would be the dot product
of the second column with the output vector.
המערכות הליניאריות, זה
Now, even though this idea breaks down for
מכוון אותנו לכיוון
של משהו לחפש:
geometric understanding for the coordinates
האם יש 00:05:37,780
of our input vector which remains unchanged
after the transformation?
--&gt; 00:05:42,780 81
If your mind has been mulling over determinants,
you might think of this clever idea: Take
וקטור חלופי, i-hat,
the parallelogram defined by the first basis
ווקטור הקלט המסתורין
[איקס; y].
השטח של המקבילית הזו
1, times the height perpendicular to that
הוא הבסיס שלה, 00:05:59,990
base, which is the y-coordinate of our input
vector.
--&gt; 00:06:03,460 86
So, the area of this parallelogram is sort
of a screwy roundabout way to describe the
כדי לדבר על קואורדינטות,
vector’s y-coordinate; it’s a wacky way
אבל רוץ איתי.
למעשה, ליתר דיוק, אתה
think of the signed area of this parallelogram,
צריך 00:06:19,690 --&gt;
in the sense described by the determinant
video.
00:06:22,440 90 להסתכל
That way, a vector with negative y-coordinate
would correspond to a negative area for this
על המקבילית המתפרשת
parallelogram.
על ידי הווקטור
Symmetrically, if you
ושל וקטור הבסיס
השני, j-hat, השטח שלו
will be the x-coordinate of the vector.
00:06:45,099 -- &gt;
Again, it’s a strange way to represent the
x-coordinate, but you’ll see what it buys
00:06:49,370 95 96
us in a moment.
יהיה לקחת את
Here’s what this would look like in three-dimensions:
Ordinarily the way you might think of one
תוצר הנקודות שלו
of a vector’s coordinate, say its z-coordinate,
עם וקטור הבסיס
הסטנדרטי השלישי, k-hat.
אבל במקום זאת,
creates with the other two basis vectors,
קחו בחשבון את
i-hat and j-hat.
המקבילית 00:07:11,870 --&gt;
If you think of the square with area 1 spanned
by i-hat and j-hat as the base of this guy,
00:07:13,569 00:07:13,569 --&gt;
its volume is the same its height, which is
the third coordinate of our vector.
00:07:20,030 102 קואורדינטה
Likewise, the wacky way to think about any
אחרת של
וקטור זה היא
all the basis vectors other than the one you’re
ליצור מקבילית בין
looking for, and get its volume.
וקטור זה ל-00:
Or, rather, we should talk about the signed
volume of these parallelepipeds, in the sense
07:34,950 --&gt; 00:07:37,900
described in the determinant video, where
the order in which you list the three vectors
00:07:37,900 --&gt; 00:07:42,490
matters and you’re using the right-hand
107 כלל.
ככה קואורדינטות שליליות עדיין הגיוניות.
אוקיי, אז למה
and volumes like this?
לחשוב על
As you apply some matrix transformation, the
areas of the parallelograms don’t stay the
קואורדינטות כאזורים
same, they may get scaled up or down.
00:07:56,000 --&gt;
But(!), and this is a key idea of determinants,
all these areas get scaled by the same amount.
00:08:02,039 112
Namely, the determinant of our transformation
113 מטריצה.
לדוגמה, אם אתה
spanned by the vector where your first basis
מסתכל על
vector lands, which is the first column of
the matrix, and the transformed version of
המקבילית 00:08:17,850
[x; y], what is its area?
--&gt; 00:08:22,850
Well, this is the transformed version of that
parallelogram we were looking at earlier,
117 118
whose area was the y-coordinate of the mystery
וקטור הקלט.
אז השטח שלו
transformation multiplied by that value.
יהיה הקובע של
So, the y-coordinate of our mystery input
vector is the area of this parallelogram,
00:08:39,080 --&gt;
spanned by the first column of the matrix
and the output vector, divided by the determinant
00:08:44,590 122 ארצות
of the full transformation.
וקטור הקלט המסתורין,
And how do you get this area?
זה כל
Well, we know the coordinates for where the
הפואנטה של מערכת
משוואות לינארית.
אז, צור מטריצה שהעמודה
the same as that of our matrix, and whose
הראשונה שלה היא 00:09:05,670
second column is the output vector, and take
its determinant.
--&gt; 00:09:11,250 129
So look at that; just using data from the
output of the transformation, namely the columns
וקטור, נוכל לשחזר את
of the matrix and the coordinates of our output
קואורדינטת ה-y של וקטור
הקלט המסתורין שלנו.
באופן דומה, אותו רעיון יכול להביא לך את קואורדינטת ה-x.
תראה את המקבילה
which encodes the x-coordinate of the mystery
שהגדרנו מוקדם 00:09:32,580
input vector, spanned by the input vector
and j-hat.
--&gt; 00:09:36,420
The transformed version of this guy is spanned
by the output vector and the second column
135 כפול בדטרמיננטה
of the matrix, and its area will have been
של המטריצה.
אז קואורדינטת ה-x של
is this area divided by the determinant of
וקטור הקלט המסתורין
the transformation.
שלנו 00:09:52,000 --&gt; 00:09:53,980
Symmetric to what we did before, you can compute
the area of that output parallelogram by creating
00:09:53,980 --&gt; 00:09:58,900
a new matrix whose first column is the output
vector, and whose second column is the same
140 רווח, המספרים שאנו
as the original matrix.
רואים במערכת הליניארית
So again, just using data from the output
המקורית שלנו, אנו
יכול לשחזר את קואורדינטת
of our mystery input vector.
ה-x 00:10:13,600 --&gt;
This formula for finding the solutions to
a linear system of equations is known as Cramer’s
00:10:18,440 145 146 הוא
rule.
4+2, שזה 6,
Here, just to sanity check ourselves, plug
in the numbers here.
והקביעה התחתונה היא 2,
The determinant of that top altered matrix
כך שקואורדינטת ה-x
צריכה להיות 3.
ואכן, במבט לאחור על
we started with, it’s x-coordinate is 3.
וקטור הקלט ההוא
Likewise, Cramer’s rule suggests the y-coordinate
should be 4/2, or 2, and that is indeed the
00:10:35,910 --&gt; 00:10:43,850
y-coordinate of the input vector we started
with here.
151 ואני ממליץ לך
The case with three dimensions is similar,
בחום לעצור לחשוב
על זה בעצמך.
הנה, אני אתן לך קצת מומנטום.
יש לנו את הטרנספורמציה
a 3x3 matrix, and a known output vector, given
הידועה הזו, הניתנת
by the right side of our linear system, and
we want to know what input vector lands on
על ידי 00:11:02,780
this output vector.
--&gt; 00:11:07,580 157 158
If you think of, say, the z-coordinate of
the input vector as the volume of this parallelepiped
וקטור, מה קורה
spanned by i-hat, j-hat, and the mystery input
לנפח של מקבילי
זה לאחר הטרנספורמציה?
איך אתה יכול לחשב את הנפח החדש הזה?
באמת, עצרו והקדישו
the details of generalizing this to higher
רגע לחשוב
dimensions; finding an expression for each
coordinate of the solution to larger linear
00:11:32,200 --&gt; 00:11:37,330
systems.
164 165
Thinking through more general cases and convincing
yourself that it works is where all the learning
איזה בחור ב-YouTube
will happen, much more so than listening to
יעבור שוב
על ההיגיון.